<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coffee | Razor Sharp Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/blog/categories/coffee/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-27T20:53:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rzrsharp.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Reidy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year in Coffee]]></title>
    <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/2012/01/12/a-year-in-coffee.html"/>
    <updated>2012-01-12T13:48:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rzrsharp.net/2012/01/12/a-year-in-coffee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year was the first that I dove deeply into the coffee world, turning what
was previously an interest into a full-blown passion. While I had previously
ground beans at home and brewed in a french press, I decided sometime in 2010
that I wanted to learn more. Going into 2011, I started brewing with an
aeropress and chemex, upgraded my grinder to a Baratza Virtuoso, and furthered my coffee knowledge by reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/God-Cup-Obsessive-Perfect-Coffee/dp/0470173580">God in a Cup</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Uncommon-Grounds-History-Coffee-Transformed/dp/0465054676">Uncommon Grounds</a>. I began taking notes on my home brews and asking questions at coffee bars. And I bought <em>lots</em> of coffee. Lots and lots and lots of coffee.</p>

<p><img src="http://s3.cheeryobservations.com/coffee2011_redone.jpg" alt="Lots of coffee" /></p>

<p>Meaghin <a href="http://www.cheeryobservations.com/photography/2011-coffee-more-coffee-than-weeks-in-the-year/">has more pictures and a full rundown of our 2011 coffee purchases</a>, but I wanted to highlight a few bags in particular.</p>

<p><img src="http://s3.cheeryobservations.com/coffee2011_15.jpg" alt="Coava and Wrecking Ball" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.wreckingballcoffee.com/">Wrecking Ball Coffee Roasters</a> is a new enterprise from Trish Rothgeb and Nick
Cho; I was lucky enough to get one of the first bags they shipped this year.
Their coffee presented a perfect example of what makes me love Ethiopian
coffees, offering a pleasantly light body without being too acidic. I like to
compare good east African coffees to pinot noir &ndash; almost all have a juiciness
to them, but the best are balanced with strong bass notes. I loved
Wrecking Ball&rsquo;s fully biodegradable package. But beyond the coffee itself,
I was happy to order from Wrecking Ball because of Nick Cho. Cho used to run
the amazing Murky Coffee in Arlington, VA, which I visited very frequently when
I lived in the DC area. Ironically, I didn&rsquo;t drink much coffee at the time, having
been exposed to some swill in college. But Murky is what enticed me to learn
more: the intoxicating smell of freshly ground Counter Culture coffee, the
precise movements of the baristas as they brewed espressos, the clear passion
of everyone involved. Drinking the Wrecking Ball made me feel as if I were
making up for the coffee I never enjoyed at Murky.</p>

<p>If Murky induced my coffee passion, <a href="http://coavacoffee.com">Coava</a> revealed the heights to which this
passion could be taken. I drank Coava&rsquo;s David Mancia from Honduras early in the
year; later, I would visit Coava&rsquo;s Portland shop in person. The David Mancia
completely blew my mind. Even in my early days of home-brewing, I couldn&rsquo;t
screw this coffee up: chocalate, berries, an amazing finish, thick and juicy
and succulent. I couldn&rsquo;t wait to see how Coava&rsquo;s shop measured up to the
coffee they roasted, and found one of my favorite coffee shops in the country.
I can&rsquo;t wait to go back.</p>

<p><img src="http://s3.cheeryobservations.com/coffee2011_21.jpg" alt="Coffee Collective" /></p>

<p>One of the highlights of 2011 was my trip to Copenhagen with Meaghin. Before the
trip, I greatly anticipated experiencing Danish culture, perhaps
most intrigued by their coffee culture. Almost everywhere we bought coffee in
Copenhagen, we felt pleased with the product, but <a href="http://thecoffeecollective.dk/">Coffee Collective</a> is an
entity unto itself. We visited their new location in Torvehallerne, a glorious
outdoor food market, a few times, trying various coffee drinks on each visit;
the Kieni from Nyeri, Kenya proved particularly delicious.</p>

<p>Two weeks into 2012 and as many bags brewed; I&rsquo;m currently finishing up a great
roast from <a href="http://www.cafegrumpy.com">Cafe Grumpy</a>, from Finca La Coqueta in
Columbia. I look forward to finding out what my favorites will be <em>this</em> year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
