<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: TDD | Razor Sharp Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/blog/categories/tdd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-25T17:08:14-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rzrsharp.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Reidy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing and Node: Why Do We Test?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/2013/07/16/testing-and-node-why-do-we-test.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-16T16:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rzrsharp.net/2013/07/16/testing-and-node-why-do-we-test</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why do we test our code?</p>

<p>The question itself seems sacrilegious in today&rsquo;s developer culture. Admitting
that you aren&rsquo;t building a comprehensive suite of unit and integration tests,
let alone not testing <em>first</em>, amounts to hanging a giant &ldquo;newb&rdquo; sign around
your neck. But sacred cows in any culture can lead to stagnation and a lack of
innovation; if you can&rsquo;t provide good cause for a practice that&rsquo;s demanded of
you, why bother doing it?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve worked on a number of different projects, spanning maturity levels,
technologies, and team sizes. While most have employed some degree of testing,
I can&rsquo;t think of a single one that employed what would be considered a &ldquo;robust
test suite&rdquo;. Certainly, open source libraries to which I&rsquo;ve contributed (and
the ones I&rsquo;ve created) have almost all included solid unit test coverage. But
there&rsquo;s a gap between what many product teams and consulting agencies preach
(&ldquo;We test all our code all the time, and only want developers who believe in
testing!&rdquo;) and what they practice (&ldquo;We&rsquo;ve got to get this feature out the door,
forget the tests for now.&rdquo;).</p>

<p>What makes the testing question more complicated is that you can never
fully-automate your way to safety. No matter how comprehensive your tests,
you&rsquo;re going to need a QA team. The most glaring need for QA is the fact that
you can&rsquo;t test the appearance of an app &mdash; and with the rise of the responsive
web, testing appearance (and by extension, usability) becomes even more
important. If you need to spend resources on QA-ing an app anyway, why should
your development team spend extra time writing tests (or testing first) when
they could instead be building features or fixing bugs?</p>

<p>The most compelling answer I&rsquo;ve found to this question comes from Sandi Metz in
her book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Object-Oriented-Design-Ruby-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321721330/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374015857&amp;sr=1-1">Practical Object-Oriented Design in Ruby</a>.
It&rsquo;s probably not surprising that a strong case for testing comes from a
Rubyist; the Ruby community has been loudly preaching test-first Agile
methodologies for years. But Metz articulates ideas in a way that increases
their poignancy. &ldquo;Tests give you confidence to refactor constantly,&rdquo; she
writes. This idea takes the common catchphrase of testing &mdash; &ldquo;red, green,
refactor&rdquo; &mdash; and turns it on its head. Instead of refactoring being a <em>part</em> of
testing, refactoring becomes the <em>point</em> of testing. &ldquo;The true purpose of
testing,&rdquo; Metz argues, &ldquo;is to reduce costs.&rdquo;</p>

<p>As a Node developer, the idea that testing provides you freedom to refactor is
entirely compelling. As I wrote in <a href="http://rzrsharp.net/2013/07/02/private-github-repos-with-npm-and-heroku.html">my article on using private Github
repositories for web application
submodules</a>,
Node developers are constantly on the prowl to refactor common bits of logic
into their own encapsulated components. By test-driving feature development,
you make it significantly easier to break out common modules:</p>

<ol>
<li>Test from the outside in: integration, then unit 2. Implement the feature
(make the tests pass) 3. Isolate code that&rsquo;s useful elsewhere, break it off
into its own module, confirm the tests still pass.</li>
</ol>


<p>In Node-land, &ldquo;red-green-refactor&rdquo; becomes &ldquo;red-green-refactor-publish
[module]&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Further, building proper test coverage may require some additional time from
your development team, but it should also decrease the pressure on your QA team
&mdash; and help everyone involved by reducing coordination costs. Think of a
scenario in which one developer bumps up an application dependency to a newer
version in order to implement a new feature (or fix a bug). The developer
sanity checks the application to see if the new version causes any problems
elsewhere in the app; finding none, the updated dependency is added to the
app&rsquo;s manifest and deployed. A week later, a bug report comes in that&rsquo;s vetted
and validated by a member of the QA team, who then needs to coordinate with
multiple developers to identify the cause of the bug (a regression from the
bumped dependency), fix it, and confirm the fix. The cost of coordinating a fix
to this regression clearly outweighs the cost of writing tests in the first
place, and this scenario is of the sort that automated testing can easily
address. In the Node ecosystem, where we frequently rely on many small
third-party modules, it&rsquo;s especially important to automatically test that our
integration with these modules is always working.</p>

<p>But testing can&rsquo;t reduce costs if we aren&rsquo;t efficient testers. And being an
efficient tester is only partially dependent on your knowledge of good OO
design; it is equally important to have a full and proper understanding of the
tools with which you need to test.</p>

<p>Which brings me to the point of this post. The Node community has a very
effective toolbox for testing first, testing well, and testing comprehensively.
But despite the capabilities of these tools, there&rsquo;s very little discussion on
the web of how to use them. An introduction to Mocha or Jasmine doesn&rsquo;t really
explain how to use them to TDD a Node app, and it certainly doesn&rsquo;t explain how
to integrate these libraries into a continuous-deployment setup with Grunt.</p>

<p>In the next few posts, I&rsquo;ll be stepping through my own &ldquo;best practices&rdquo; for
testing a Node app. I&rsquo;ll be the first to admit that there are probably better
approaches to testing, and I&rsquo;ll be quite happy to receive feedback, but
hopefully this series can serve as a guide to get the Node testing discussion
started. If there&rsquo;s anything you&rsquo;re particularly curious about, please let me
know and I&rsquo;ll try to address it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
