<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Github | Razor Sharp Design]]></title>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/blog/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-25T17:29:55-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://rzrsharp.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Reidy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Private Github Repos with NPM &amp; Heroku]]></title>
    <link href="http://rzrsharp.net/2013/07/02/private-github-repos-with-npm-and-heroku.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T16:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rzrsharp.net/2013/07/02/private-github-repos-with-npm-and-heroku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you spend time coding in the Node.js ecosystem, you become increasingly
reliant on small modules, both consuming them and building them yourself.
This habit of building and composing modular toolsets begins
to extend beyond library code, and you start to think of web application code
as a collection of modules. Data models, for example, can be easily
packaged into a separate Node module for re-use in related applications
(and to chunk off a set of application dependencies).</p>

<p>Seeing code that can be broken off into its own module, you dutifully follow
your Node.js instincts, break off the code, and move it to its own directory.
You create a new private Github repo for this small module, and push it up.
But how do you re-integrate this new (actively developed) sub-project back into
its containing projects?</p>

<p>NPM has always made it easy to manage Node modules as Git submodules. The NPM
<a href="https://npmjs.org/api/submodule.html">submodule</a> command will add a package
dependency as a Git submodule, and from then on will basically ignore the
containing folder, letting you update and modify the package as you will.
There&rsquo;s also NPM&rsquo;s <a href="https://npmjs.org/api/link.html">link</a> command, which will
install a package dependency from a symlink on your development machine rather
than from the npmjs.org repository.</p>

<p>But when it comes to the common use case of deploying a web app with a Git submodule package to Heroku, things get complicated:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Your submodules are private Github repositories, so you need to get access
to them without sacrificing account security;</p></li>
<li><p>Assuming you get around the first challenge, Git submodules are autotomatically
installed on Heroku deploy, and then NPM will stubbornly refuse to install the
submodule dependencies;</p></li>
<li><p>If you&rsquo;re using <code>npm shrinkwrap</code> to lock down your app dependencies, the
presence of Git submodules or linked directories screws up the shrinkwrap
metadata and makes install difficult.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There&rsquo;s a very specific approach you need to take to work around these issues.</p>

<p>First, there&rsquo;s the account security issue. HTTPS access to your Github
repositories allows you to use a username and password instead of an SSH key,
but then you&rsquo;re putting your account credentials in plaintext &ndash; an
obvious problem. Thankfully, you can use Github&rsquo;s OAuth token support to better
secure your repositories. Follow <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-an-oauth-token-for-command-line-use">Github&rsquo;s instructions</a>
for creating a token with &ldquo;repo&rdquo; scope. Then, in your package.json, add the following for your submodule:</p>

<p><code>javascript
  "package-name": "git+https://&lt;github_token&gt;:x-oauth-basic@github.com/&lt;user&gt;/&lt;repo&gt;.git"
</code></p>

<p>Great! Now you&rsquo;ve got an installable submodule that can be deployed to Heroku
and/or shrinkwrapped without a problem.</p>

<p>But if your module is changing frequently (e.g. its under active development along
with its parent project), you probably want a &ldquo;live&rdquo; version of the code in
your project folder. Using a Git submodule solves some problems but introduces
others. The best approach is to use <code>npm link</code> to link a checked-out copy of
the submodule from elsewhere on your filesystem.</p>

<p>Sadly, <code>link</code>-ing to a project will cause problems for you if you use <code>npm
shrinkwrap</code>. Shrinkwrap tracks the origin of each node module, and when you
link, you lose that nice OAuth-ified Github url. There&rsquo;s only one way around
this problem, and while it feels a bit hacky, it works. Add that <code>git+https</code>
url from above (the one with the OAuth token) to a <code>_from</code> field in each
submodule&rsquo;s <code>package.json</code>. <code>shrinkwrap</code> will defer to this field whenever it&rsquo;s
run.</p>

<p>So the succint list of steps:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Create a Github OAuth token.</p></li>
<li><p>Add Github module dependencies to your main app&rsquo;s <code>package.json</code> file with the URL scheme specified above.</p></li>
<li><p>Add the same URL to your submodule packages' <code>_from</code> fields.</p></li>
<li><p><code>npm link</code> the submodules if you&rsquo;re actively working on them.</p></li>
<li><p>Deploy to Heroku as normal and everything will just work.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>&hellip;Hopefully.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
